I guess we have no one in the room with
us so Jon Vevey aqui we are now
recording a podcast and this is the
first time we've met and I'm honored
you've taking the time this is very
exciting for me this is the first video
online podcast I've actually recorded
they by the way it's all been in person
oh wow well yeah that's great yeah it's
great to meet you Tim I appreciated our
email conversation I'm looking forward
to our discussion yeah right and look
there's so much to talk about and now we
have that invisible party in the room
and and some of those people will be
familiar with your work I know a lot of
my listeners won't be apart from the
ones I've managed to get along to the
meetups I am holding to watch your
lecture series and discuss it which has
been quite interesting too and I've got
some questions from the people who've
been attending that we'll get to a bit
later on but for the benefit of people
who aren't familiar with your work I
thought perhaps you could talk a little
bit about in particular the context the
arena if you like using your terminology
you take yourself to be acting in or
stepping into at the moment sure okay
well I mean I'll tell you just a little
bit for your listeners Who I am I mean I
am an assistant professor the teachers
scream at the teaching stream at the
University of Toronto and so I do I'm 60
percent in cognitive psych login' of
psychology and forty percent in
cognitive science and so I I study
cognition very deeply and the aspect of
cognition that I'm very interested in is
this central ability to zero in on
relevant information and how that
actually functions to give us this sense
of meaning the sense of connectedness to
ourselves to each other to reality and
that and how that machinery is
simultaneously something that can be a
vehicle for self-deception in us and it
can also be a vehicle for self
transcendence and the cultivation of
wisdom and the enhancement of that sense
of meaning that's that's you know in
concert with a kind of optimization of
our functioning in the world so I'm
interested in all of that
because the arena that I see myself
addressing that knowledge towards is the
meaning crisis that I think is by
setting western civilization for lack of
a better term and this is basically a
loss of an overarching framework of
worldview attunement of our
understanding of who we are and what the
world is and how those fit together in
such a way that we get an overall
guiding structure and legitimate sort of
a legitimization of our projects of
meaning making and the cultivation of
wisdom and virtue and I think what I'm
trying to understand and trying to help
other people understand is both
historically how did we get here how did
we get into this crisis and then you
know and how is that expressing itself
now and things like the mental health
crisis the opioid crisis addiction
crisis right you know sort of the the
the sense of that simultaneously you
know everything is politicized but we're
losing faith in all of our political
institutions and processes the sense
that in the technical sense
that Frankfort uses it is pervasive and
growing everywhere also positive signs
like the mindfulness revolution the
psychedelics revolution the authentic
discourse revolution all of this so the
historical you know genealogy that's led
to this current situation about the
positive and negative symptoms of it and
then also the other thing I'm trying to
do is to understand you know trying to
get a deep cognitive scientific
understanding of this meaning making
machinery that I mentioned a few minutes
ago and well like how we can use the
best science we have to do two related
things transplant and recover from the
wisdom traditions of the past east and
west sets of psycho technologies and
practices that could help us respond to
the meaning crisis and also hopefully
engineer new ecologies of practices so
that we can figure out
how we can once again legitimate and
enhance the cultivation of wisdom and
meaning making within the scientific
worldview that we now have come to
accept as the dominant world view of of
Western culture so that that's basically
the idea yeah beautiful that was an
excellent summary I've been doing my
best to give a summary like that before
each week when you people arrive and
it's been a difficult process but you've
definitely got it down there yeah I hope
so it's it's a tricky thing it's a very
long and complex argument and many many
people have collaborated with me on it
so yeah any sort of variables I'm trying
to manage all at once when I when I'm
answering these questions yes no
absolutely um look there's there's so
many places we could get into here one
of the things that came up was that yes
it's the case that in science it has
historically speaking being a little
detached let's say from what's really
meaningful it's looking to give us truth
about what the world is proposition II
but can become detached from what we
should do about it or how we should
relate to it so there's different kinds
of knowing that I know you like to
emphasize which is one of the first key
cognitive switch ups I think that it's
helpful for people to become open to
let's say the quality of experience and
taking experience seriously from a
perspective of knowing so I'm sure you
know you will comment on that but but
what I'm trying to get to is is in fact
yes it's important that that's the
conversation about meaning and and
states of consciousness is one that can
be made sensible to science and what
science can make sense of to be made
sensible to people who are experiencing
things in a really important way but
politically and culturally the forum's
we have for having conversations that
take place in this place of meaning of
this place of meaning making of Co
participation with each other in the
process of meaning making are certainly
is certainly an institution
it seems like it's broken down and in
fact to some degree it's not clear that
it's ever been really firmly established
at least at least well we can think of
historically speaking although it was
just men Athenian men who participated
in it you have the the forum's they
participated in back there and and that
was sort of this interesting merging of
the cultural setting and the political
setting but what what I'm interested in
John is is is do you think about the the
possibility that what could be helpful
in our world is one in which people of
learning but importantly people who are
willing to be vulnerable and authentic
with respect to how they discuss matters
of importance both existentially but
also who attempt to make these
commensurate with domain-specific
scientifically literate ways of
understanding the world a forum where
that kind of conversation takes place
where you have sort of real epistemic
authenticity and a real humanism built
into them I'm not sure we have that in
our society and I'm interested in what
you think about that and whether or not
because I think your work in some sense
is laying an important you're you're
doing something really high-level
scaffolding you're making legitimate
different areas of inquiry into what is
fundamentally just people looking to
connect with each other
authentically and take their individual
practices and build them into
communities and I see you as knitting
together these disparate areas and I see
being idea idealistic about things room
to move in and develop forums that are
that are over different kind and I'm not
sure exactly how to say it but I think I
sort of I'm getting at the point to you
if you if you understand what I'm in the
image I'm conjuring forward here well I
think you you expressed that very
eloquently so thank you for that
articulation yeah I mean I I take that
very seriously and and thank you for
suggesting that my work is trying to
create sort of a
I'm holding for what you're talking
about yeah I'm very interested in the
the project and the prospect of creating
I'll use your now in the forum right a
place of some kind where this kind of
dialogue becomes much more prevalent and
much more coherent with and conducive to
a way of life because that's ultimately
what I see so I think I hope this is
addressing your point yes so so what
what what's happening now and one of the
gifts of the video series and some of
the and all the podcasts and the video
interviews and such is I'm getting to
meet a lot of people who are doing
exactly what you're talking about yes
they write they are trying to create
places institutions communities sets of
practices new psycho technologies right
reverse-engineer our cognition and our
consciousness you know in our community
in in powerful ways and and and I I
don't I don't want to take undue credit
i I've been fortunate to be put in touch
with these people and I'm starting to
see how how much there is a grass roots
I hate to say that it sounds so
hackneyed but there's a grass roots
movement right to create networks to
create things like secular monasteries
to create regular meetings intellectual
existential philosophical Sapientia
exploration mutual affordance mutual
scuffle I'm meeting these people all
over the place the fact that our
political and economic machinery is
ignoring this to a large degree I think
is telling again it's a telling symptom
of the meeting crisis in an important
way but I do think that I personally
have become much more optimistic about
the fact that I think we are moving
towards trying to figure out how to
craft the sort of fundamental conceptual
and practical in the sense of practices
right vocabulary and grammar of this
forum that you've talked about so many
different things are happening I'm like
III this morning I was talking to a
gentleman
he owns a dojo and he is and we are
meeting regularly and we're talking
about how to translate the stuff from
the series into okay what's this what's
a whole set of interlocking you know
pedagogical practices I can give to
these kids so that the dojo becomes not
just a place of learning a martial art
and movement practices but you know a
place of you know for actually giving
kids a community where they're
cultivating what dojos used to be wisdom
and a capacity right for addressing the
meeting crisis and that and that's
precisely because the parents and the
kids were coming to him and asking him
for this I've talked to somebody he
belongs to a community of secular
monasteries trying to bring back that
institution that we used to have in the
West the monastery where people would go
precisely the form of community of you
know deep that integrated deep
intellectual discourse with you know
tremendous you know Spiritual Exercises
for transforming cognition and
consciousness so more and more I see
this happening and and again I I don't
know what what what I'm trying to
articulate here other than a combination
of a sense of gratitude appreciation for
the fact that my work seems to be you
know helping provoke this to some degree
or at least give people a vocabulary for
articulate and expressing an age giving
them waste ways to connect together so
this has all been just you know an
unforeseen but very welcomed consequence
of the series and so I think I'm
participating in I don't I'm trying to
be cautious as a not trake take
authority for this but I am
participating in people trying to
address the very question you you raised
mmm beautiful John got them so many
things to go on
hmm guys see I have these metaphysical
problems or things I'd like to talk to
you about but before I do I should just
say that for people listening and who
are based in Melbourne and are
interested in what John what you have
just outlined here this is something I
am also participating in doing so for
people who want to come in person and be
involved in just this sort of creation
you can get in contact it's worth saying
just because it oh of course I fully
endorse that yeah and the other thing
about that as well which is you know I'm
networking to the best degree I can with
people around the world who are doing
these things and I think there's will be
a lot of benefit and getting together
for group discussions to discuss these
sort of things and share the successes
of failures of things moving forward I
don't look at this stuff at all as
competition I think if you do then and I
don't think anybody in this space is and
I think I'm I'm desperately interested
in in learning as quickly as possible
the most appropriate ways to do this
because there's actually an awful lot of
vulnerability involved and here okay
here is where I can begin to get close
to them to the metaphysical things that
I think the two of us together might be
perhaps some fun grappling with and one
way to get into it is to consider just
how vulnerable philosophizing is I think
it was Nietzsche who said that
philosophy is something like the
revealing of the unconscious prejudice
of a philosopher or something like this
and I think broadly that notion is is
very true and for other reasons besides
I personally get quite blurred with the
line between psychology and metaphysics
but there's something but-but-but-but
move it to this place of speaking
authentically vulnerably and seeking
truth in that in that way which is which
which always bears forth that ultimately
there's something about this this frame
there's something about this experience
that I'm deeply uncertain about right
and I'm I'm I'm tenderly stepping out
attempting to stay
to some degrees strong with where I am
here so we might build some framework
together there's something about this
that seems to me to me to be like a joke
like genuinely revealing something quite
deep about the psyche the more you go
along with this and there's something
very personally vulnerable about being
in these spaces and the well in some
sense I think in some basic ways there's
a distribution of where we are a
distribution as a as a population and I
think your your your core most
differentiations often are tied to some
of your deepest personal traumas and
then perhaps there's a transpersonal
domain as well but but the point I'm
trying to make is that there is a
vulnerability to this certain kind of
seeking and so it would be helpful to be
as cognizant as possible of all the
people who are honestly trying to build
these structures and to communicate with
them about it and so one thing you know
I personally would love to would love to
be involved in in that kind of
conversation but I suppose that moves us
in one way and not and not another way
more appropriate for this conversation
here so so I guess maybe a personal
question I'd like to ask is is do you
feel that vulnerability in certain kinds
of philosophical discussion because
these we can hold things so deeply and I
wonder the kind of things they're
attached to and I'll leave that broad
for now because I think ultimately that
will take us into where I want to go
yeah that's that's great as a question I
mean I mean that I'd like to reply in
two ways to that question I'd like to
reply personally and then I'd like to
reply philosophically but you'll see
that I hope you'll see that there are
they're deeply connected yeah I mean
that's that's been another aspect of
this even the video series that has was
again to some degree unanticipated so I
know this is an odd thing for what I do
as a profession and even with this video
series but I'm by nature very quite
socially phobic
[Laughter]
what I've done what I've done is I've
created this powerful professional
persona that I use in order to help deal
with that you know and and but what I
had not foreseen is the degree to which
that particular deficit in my
personality structure would be
exacerbated and called to the fore by
putting up this video series because you
see when you're in the classroom right
that persona is you know directly in
contact with people I'm getting direct
feedback I second haina yeah yeah
but when you put out the the video it's
like whoa and so all of that hit me
in a way that was psychologically are
actually quite quite unpleasant for me I
I don't want your listeners to
misunderstand me I'm deeply appreciative
of the opportunity to do the series and
the response both quantitatively and
qualitatively that I'm getting but I'm
trying to answer your question as
honestly as I can so a lot of that a lot
of this has been sort of very very you
know a little for lack of a better
adjective it with has been
psychologically unpleasant yeah me yeah
in a very powerful way and so there's
there's definitely that aspect to it now
that I think is connected to a
philosophical point I want to make and
I'm referring to work that you've heard
if or some of your listeners might have
heard I referred to in the video series
and many of my talks this is the work by
la Paul on transformative experience and
and then I try I know and I've talked to
Lori in person a bit about this and I
think it's uncomfortable about talking
this way integrating her work with what
you alluded to earlier these different
kinds of knowing and she talks about you
know in the genuine transformative
experiences we face these we face this
issue that we face a kind of
perspectival ignorance so if I'm a
parent and I'm just you know if I'm
choosing whether or not I'm gonna have a
child
I don't know what it what I'm what it's
going to be like to have a child I don't
have that perspective knowledge right
that perspective of knowing and I don't
know who I'm going to be because one of
the things I mean I've had two kids one
of the things that happens when you have
a child and you you authentically enter
into the project of trying your best of
your parent is you will fundamentally
change who you are and what you value
and what you prefer
so she says look you're ignorant in
these two ways you're you you're you
you're ignorant of the perspective of
knowing you don't know what it's gonna
be like you don't know what that
salience landscape is gonna be like and
you don't know who you're going to be
you don't know the way in which you're
going what like what your your
preference hierarchy is going to be
right you some of the machinery of
yourself is gonna be fundamentally
reconfigured so then she says you're
caught in this you caught in this
situation right you're caught in that if
you don't do it you don't know what
you're missing and if you decide to do
it you don't know what you're going to
be losing yes and that's a deep and
profound kind of vulnerability that
you're in right now I think that that's
I think that also interacts with another
thing we get into right which is you
know when we get into a kind of
existential inertia where we have
propositional knowledge but we don't
know how to translate that into the
perspective all right and participatory
knowing and this is this is the this is
the development that usually faces
people going into therapy they know
right the level of their beliefs but
they don't know how to get there the
answer they don't know how to turn those
into a viable arena of action and being
yeah so they have that kind of
existential inertia and that's also a
kind of vulnerability because you feel
your agency slipping out of your fingers
right because you're unable to move
yourself in that fundamental way and so
I think when we confront the kinds of
things that you and I are talking about
here we're confronting you know that egg
that that profound kind of perspective
on participatory ignorance that Lori
talks about and we're taught but we're
also confronting a profound kind of
perspectival and participatory inertia
and
that is deeply deeply distressing and
those two can lock together and
reinforce each other so I think we can
experience a very profound kind of
vulnerability in the face of the kind of
transformation we are seriously
considering here yes no beautiful I'm
with you and I do think I've read parts
of La Paul's work there on
transformative experience and the
distinction she makes between well she
has like the the personal transformation
and epistemic transformation which I
think two of the do sort of cover what
you've said there which is very light
and helpful in the way that analytic
philosophy is tight and helpful good all
right here's here's another way that
I've personally found the vulnerability
in my own putting things forward and
it's gonna open up more to I'm gonna so
I am um I've read a bit of young and
young has influenced me quite a lot I
would say yep partly been through I've
been through like like through Jungian
therapy I went I put myself through
Jungian therapy I also attend I've
attended multiple workshops on you know
Union therapeutic practice I'm not
claiming to be an expert but I do have
an insider's understanding of the
process yes yes and some of my
collaborators like Anderson Todd are
genuine Union Allen analysts and
theorists yes yeah I mean I think I mean
for for one reason among many young at
least from a Western perspective was one
of of course there are others Alfred
North Whitehead is also an influence on
mine but he was one of the thinkers
feelers really who's looking to take the
internal world seriously but still he
make that comprehensible as best he
could in his own language to the
scientific perspective and so there is
this is kind of an early and I think he
went incredibly far farther than I can
go he went incredibly far in in in
trying to in some sense do this reom
bedding into the one world she might be
there between the internal and external
I know that's
I know that's there's different ways you
could make that oppositional divide in
terms of what constitutes the two world
model but surely speaking the meaning in
terms of the internal world and the
psyche and then the external world of
bodies colliding is is is one sort of
dichotomy that we have got trapped in
but one of the terms and you get this
term of course in otherwise in different
areas of psychology but it's one of
projection and so I mean things out
there online and you know they've been
watched a lot fewer that then then then
your videos have but one in particular
with a well-known figure who you might
have know personally given that he's
Canadian basis Gabor Matta who's a
physician and it's done a lot of work on
trauma and addiction and he has and a
big online following and I've heard of
I've heard of him and I've I have not
I'm not claiming to know any of his work
but I've had people refer me to him
before yes please continue I believe
he's he's helped a lot of people in
conceptualizing it addiction and trauma
very helpfully I have no doubt about
that but when him and I spoke in the
podcast and I think it's a fairly
entertaining watch there was a little
tension between us partly because I was
attempting to articulate a position that
was not in total contrast to what he was
putting forward but was was part of the
dialogical process I think required to
get to where I felt at the time wasn't
the right synthesis but the point I'm
just making is there was that there was
a little bit of tension between us there
and he has a lot of fans and and so it's
very interesting to see what the people
write about you and pick up on you in an
environment like that so from what was
flyy perspective honestly really trying
to engage in a discussion all of a
sudden then you're you're you're placing
yourself forward in just that one
perspective of how you appeared then and
almost every little different part of
you is getting picked apart and so the
point I'm making is you make yourself a
martyr isn't the right word you are you
are whatever hooks you do have for
projection you're kind of like a magnet
like a medium for
Justin's really a you become a magnet
for projection right and is that the
point yes well yes that's that right and
so how do you mean that just seems like
a necessary sacrifice in some sense but
it is a very interesting one I just
wonder what your experience it's also a
dangerous one
right I mean so I mean that I mean let's
use a union term that could that could
induce you know significant inflation in
an individual yes right or if you use
other terms it could really feed a kind
of narcissism right and it could appeal
to all kinds of cognitive biases of you
know the illusion of superiority or
called you know confirmation bias so
those projections have the capacity
right - really really twist and warp a
person and so Tim from the very
beginning of it I've been very cognizant
of that and I've been very cognizant of
the dangerous both ways so the danger to
me in the kind of person I could become
as the receiver of this projection and
let's be clear I mean I do I have and do
receive some very very you know you know
very powerful very superlative things
and so that can be like that could and
you can see what people are doing right
and and they're confusing what I've been
saying with me as a person and all that
all that machinery that we normally find
in projection and then there's also the
reverse which is right you you have to
be you have to be responsible for how
people are responding to you you can't
just sort of push people away because
you don't want to be a magnet for the
projections right because that that's
gonna render almost any attempt to reach
people where they are
you know just impossible I would say so
towards the first I've done I've done a
careful job of trying to know people who
I think and have gone the wrong way
and sort of by reverse template try to
avoid some of those patterns
and then I have I have gathered around
me a group of people who have have
because of deep friendship and Trust the
authority to criticize me and I've
explicitly asked them and repeatedly
asked them to be involved in this
project of keeping me you know clear and
centered on that what I do outward is I
try to make it clear that people should
focus on the arguments and the ideas and
that those ideas and arguments don't
belong solely to me mm-hmm right I'm
constantly trying to say look here's
other people that are working with me
here's other like that's why I have in
the video series that the panel's come
up right you know of the books I'm
talking about I constantly try to cite
other people that I've collaborated with
and then I constantly sort of like so I
I mean I understand in this context why
personal questions are asked because
that's what's going on here yes but
generally I when people are like in the
video series asking me questions about
me personally I don't respond to those
questions yes right right i I don't
respond to those questions in so I try
to get people focused on the argument
and focused on the set of people beyond
just me that are responsible for the
production of what people are finding
useful or helpful yes no beautiful I
think one difference between our cases
John is that you responded to my
question they're given the positive
feedback you've had on large words in my
case I was just hammered okay
well but it's going to continue to
happen and and I'm okay with that and in
many respects it's it's a wonderful
opportunity to learn although you do
actually just have to push some away
because you have to develop a bit of a
thick skin right absolutely and some of
them some comments are complete bollocks
right but some are you can kind of see
okay that's how I'm coming across here
and it's like alright why am i coming
across like this Oh
were their motives about that I was
bringing to the table that word that
were there two for not conscious to me
so what strings were pulling me what
drives you were pulling me what what
things inside were looking to develop
and maybe not had their time to be made
explicit in a particular way that were
piercing through and having their same
and I like thinking I like thinking like
this although there's a danger in it
because it's in part a sort of post hoc
analysis but the thing is is that we are
unknown to ourselves and we do develop
and in some sense you can only
understand the gestalt of what you've
been and are doing in your life by
taking this oversight this oversight
view and of course you will then I'm
sure and rightly elucidate the two two
modes or two directions of intention
let's say in meditation experience or in
mindfulness practice that can help
better fit or come up with and fit us to
the right frame of reference to
understand what our place in the world
or what the world is and I know you like
to talk about meditation as this as this
breaking up the frame and sort of
returning to a kind of in impartiality
and non identification with the
particular contents of consciousness and
then the the contemplation which was a
really nice switch up for me and it
mapped on to some work I'd done
previously although not so that anywhere
near to the degree of clarity that you
talked about these things with
contemplation as this this going out
again once the frames been broken and
attempting to grasp the world in the
right way and that we have these
revolutions of this process if we are
let's say being good little rational
cognitive agents that can help us better
fit ourselves to the to an understanding
of the situation could you you
articulated that extremely well thank
you I mean that I think yeah you you put
that very clearly
come on yeah no I mean look I am I think
this is uh crucial I genuinely think I
genuinely think what you're doing is is
crucial and I think the
that every week there's these really
tight descriptions of like for example
all right so this will be a bit of a
break up from the from the conversation
but it is something I want to ask you
because I think it's that valuable that
I want people to hear it and it's the
distinction you make between the having
mode and having needs and the being mode
and being needs for yeah this is one
where look I have a guy that comes along
to the meetup and watches this with me
very very smart guy very well educated
he works in some sort of psychological
capacity with people who have various
problems and he takes transformation
seriously from every level of analysis
physiological psychological spiritual
but even this distinction for him I
think was like a light bulb moment in
terms of well it's such a simple way to
articulate something so fundamental
about what we are that speaks
importantly to where we are often going
wrong in current culture so if you would
please the having mode and the being
mode I'd love for you to tell us about
that
ah thank you so the idea is drawn from
Erich Fromm his book you know to happen
to be but and and Fromm is clear about
this he doesn't think he's the
originator of this distinction you can
find analogous distinctions and in many
places
Steven Bachelor has a version of this
distinction in his book alone with
others an existential interpretation of
Buddhism you can find something an
allegation Gabriel Marcel so right and I
think even you could understand parts of
what Heidegger is doing using this
distinction but I think from and the
reason why I use from ways of talking
about it although I supplement it a bit
with with Boober and with Collingwood
right I think that it's a very clear and
concise way of talking about it
so Fromm's idea is that right first of
all we have to get this notion of an
existential mode right so when I'm
talking about an existential mode I'm
talking about this process of Co
identification right
I'm always assuming a particular
identity in order to exercise my agency
and I'm projecting onto the world I set
set of identities in order to make that
world
an intelligible arena for my action and
so those and this is also related to you
know Clifford Geertz his work on
worldviews right but that that deep
participatory relationship the way they
Co define and co-create each other yes
okay that's the existential mode and
that what Fromme was pointing out is we
have two fundamentally different
existential modes and these modes these
agent arena Co fitting relationships are
organized around different sets of needs
we have
and so the having needs are needs that
are met by having things exercising
control over them
ultimately often ultimately consuming
them like oxygen food water or at least
having really intimate control over them
like shelter etc right and then Fromm's
notion is well those are first of all
neither mode is right or wrong okay yes
but the having mode is right it's a
legitimate mode because we do have these
needs there's things we literally have
to consume and have power and control
over or we cease to be yes and then he
asks a really good question like what
like what is your cognitive machinery
like right and what's your existential
mode like in order to facilitate solving
this we says well what you do is you and
here I'll use some Collingwood ideas to
to make it a little bit clearer but what
I do is I give things a categorical
identity like this is a glass hmm right
and so I I can quickly and efficiently
know know how to get control over it and
manipulate it because I can put it into
a category and I can use the way in
which it's similar to all the other
glasses and the way I could replace this
with another glass so all of that
ability assign a categorical identity
and then that tells you what my
relationship is to it my relationship is
one of you know what Fromm calls like
animal intelligence that that that's not
an insult by the way right it means my
tremendous capacity to manipulate things
in the world in order to write to solve
my having needs so I have an i it
relationships of things to use an idea
from Buber now then Fromm pointed out
but we have a different set of needs he
calls the
being needs I sometimes think that it
might be more accurate to call them
becoming needs or developmental needs so
we have a need to be mature we need to
be we have a need to become mature to
develop maturity we have a need to you
know become virtuous we need to you know
we have a need to become authentic these
are these are things we need to become
so these are not these needs are not met
by controlling or manipulating these are
needs that are met through and this goes
back to something we were talking about
not that long ago these needs are met by
going through important developmental
transformations yes in in really
important ways coming up with ways in
which we overcome that existential
inertia that that existential ignorant
and fundamentally go through a process
of self transcendence and so the being
needs are met therefore by a different
framework of cognition because now I'm
not primarily trying to solve problems
in the sense of come up with an answer
of how to quickly get my goal instead
what I'm trying to do is connect myself
to reality like to the reality of who I
am and the reality out there so that I
can get this reciprocal realization so
that I and the world can Co transform
the agent in the arena can Co transform
so that I become a different you know
cognitive agent so my relationship now
is not one of animal intelligence it's
one of reflect reflective reason where
reason is this process by which we take
ourselves so when I use reason I'm not
talking about syllogistic argumentation
I'm talking about this process by which
we put ourselves through like
development in order to enhance and
optimize our capacities with respect to
the world so because I'm engaged in this
project right of making meaning because
that's what reason is doing for me mate
right and and going through this
developmental change I don't have an I
in relationship to things I want to be
connected to things so that I could
penetrate to their mystery right and and
and and the mystery that that's still
within me see the mystery is that is
that developmental of ordinance right
for these kinds of
transformations and self-transcendence
that are needed for the being mode so I
have an eye though relationship yes to
use Boober am i that my interaction with
things is not categorically but
expressively so I'll often use the this
point right presumably and this is and I
think I share this with people that's my
presumption your relationship to a deep
friend or your romantic partner is a
developmental relationship of reciprocal
realization you're both you're both
affording each other's growth and and
and and disclosure of depth both within
yourself and within the arena of your
life right and so your relationship to
your partner or to your deep friend is
not an I it categorical manipulative
relationship I wouldn't say to my
partner I wouldn't say to her you know
I'm with you because you remind me so
readily of all the other women I've ever
been with like that gives me information
so that I can efficiently and
effectively manipulate you and control
you in order to you know service my
needs like that is not making this
relationship go well I'm destroying the
relationship because that is not why she
has entered into this relationship right
she's not entered into it to solve a
problem to have control over resources
she's entered into it to become a
different person and that is of course
why I've also entered into it so here's
the issue then both modes are legitimate
what from and I would argue and this is
what Stephen Bachelor argues you know
what Buddhism and many things are
talking about is modal confusion when we
confuse when we pursue right we use the
wrong mode to pursue the needs we're
pursuing and the classic example that
Fromm uses is we pursue the being needs
from within the having mode so that you
know in order to become mature we have a
car in order to be in love we have lots
of sex right yeah right and and so what
we we can proms Point right is
that confusion serves other people in
their capacity to exploit and manipulate
us because if I can keep you trapped in
the having mode you are of course we are
being frustrated and I mean that in a
deep existential and psychological sense
you're being frustrated in your attempt
to satisfy your being needs so you what
will you do you're trapped in the having
mode and having the car isn't doing it
so it must mean that I don't have the
right car or I've got to get a new car
or a new iPhone or
right or I've got to get more likes I
have to have more likes on my social
media and so you pursue this with an
increasing frenzy and then fraud
predicts there's two responses to that
like the the the the futility and the
frustration bifurcate and you either
fall into a kind of deep despair or you
get that frustration of futility reach
this out in the only way in which you
feel you can again reconnect to reality
which is sort of a violent you know
reaction anger and you know attacking
those around you because that's sort of
the last resort you have to at least
reconnect to reality in some fundamental
way
so the modal confusion is a profound way
in which we can be deceived and and and
that deception also makes us X you know
quite exceptionally vulnerable to to
manipulation by others beautiful thank
you very much for taking us through that
I think it's incredibly valuable okay so
if you can bear with me and you might
have to help me along with this because
of our limited time remaining I want to
see if I can provide a context for a
particular sort of metaphysical
discussion so I can better understand
your position on things and sure to
share a little bit about where my not
just interests but where my capacity to
make coherence of things currently lies
with and is to do with in some important
sense what's most fundamental I suppose
it's to do with ontology but it's a
process
metaphysics we're in actually our agency
and our capacity to draw coherence into
experience might be used as an important
vehicle to gain insight into not just
psychological process of sense making
and the cognitive process of relevance
realization but perhaps to metaphysical
process itself